Did you ever wonder if certain foods
have a direct effect on your health?
Well, I’m here to
solve that mystery
since you are
the foods you eat.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Back by popular demand,
it’s our NutritionFacts Grab Bag,
where we look at the science
on a whole variety of topics
starting with a story about how to
preserve your sense of smell.
Based on a study
of nearly 2,000 people,
our sense of smell
declines as we age,
similar to our loss in vision
and hearing.
About a quarter of Americans
over the age of 50
suffer from
olfactory dysfunction,
a difficulty identifying odors,
which climbs to more than half
of individuals
between the ages
of 65 to 80,
and about 80 percent
in those over the age of 80.
And that was before COVID-19,
which affected the smell
of nearly 50 percent
of sufferers.
Typically, it was temporary,
but as many as a 15 percent
of non-hospitalized
COVID survivors
were still experiencing problems
with the ability to smell
three or more months later,
and there are cases of it
lasting for years.
As anyone with even
a simple head cold can tell you,
when you lose
your sense of smell,
you lose much of your sense
of taste as well.
Between 75 to 95 percent
of what we think of as taste,
may actually be smell.
This was all
too vividly illustrated
by the case
of Algerian War soldiers
whose tongues
were cut out,
remarkably reporting
little loss
of food and drink
flavor sensation.
But hey, if loss of smell
leads to loss of taste,
think of all the weight loss!
That was apparently the thought
behind the development
of a "novel nasal device,"
gag-inducing silicone tubes
you stick into your nostrils
to cordon off
your smell receptors.
Researchers recorded
a drop in preference
for sugary foods and beverages
along with weight loss,
but only among
the younger adults,
presumably because the sense
of smell of the older adults
was already impaired.
Making everything taste bland
may help you skip
a few doughnuts,
but the flipside
is that people
with smelling difficulties
tend to add more salt.
Older individuals
were found to require
two to three times more salt
than those who were younger
to achieve the same salty taste.
It's no wonder
that the lifetime risk
of developing
high blood pressure
may exceed 90 percent.
What can we do to preserve
our sense of smell?
Ambient air pollution
is associated with
olfactory dysfunction,
thought to explain
why nasal biopsies
from residents of Mexico City,
living and dead,
showed more lesions
and inflammatory changes
than those living
in low-pollution cities.
We may not have a choice
where we live,
but there is definitely
a direct source of air pollution
tied to loss of smell
we can all choose to avoid:
cigarette smoke.
Smell loss can have
serious consequences,
for example,
missing a gas leak, smoke,
or spoiled food.
If you have lost your sense
of smell and use natural gas,
please consider buying
a gas detector.
But, in terms of
direct disability,
most people who are affected
don't even to seem to be aware
their smell is impaired,
even when asked directly.
Nearly 8 out of 10 elderly
individuals with smell loss
thought they had
normal smell sensitivity.
Hearing loss, however,
is considered a major cause
of global disability,
ranking among
the top chronic conditions
affecting older adults.
For far too long, though,
as a National Academy
of Medicine report put it,
hearing loss has been
"relegated to the sidelines
of health care."
In our next story,
we look at how duct
tape beat out freezing
and ten other treatments
for the removal of warts.
When I was reviewing the science behind
common over-the-counter remedies
used in dermatology such as tea
tree oil for acne or nail fungus,
I was surprised to see on the same
page a section on duct tape.
Duct tape?!
The only time I remember seeing
duct tape used in a medical study
was on the identification of the gases
responsible for the odor of human farts,
which involved a collection system
comprised of gas-tight pantaloons
sealed to the skin with duct tape.
That's the study where they
assessed the wind breaking ability
of a cushion called
the Toot Trapper.
But what the dermatology journal
was talking about is warts.
Duct tape brings out our
inventive, slightly kooky side.
Given this versatility, it wasn't
so surprising a few years ago
when a group of doctors reported
that duct tape could get rid of warts.
As I noted in my last wart video,
all sorts of strange things
are purported to cure warts
because most go away on their own.
A thousand kids were
followed for two years
and two-thirds of the warts
disappeared without doing a thing.
So maybe we should
just leave them alone,
although there are cases
that may warrant treatment.
Otherwise we can just let our
own body take care of them.
Warts are caused by wart viruses, and
so spontaneous wart disappearance
is assumed to be an immune response
where our body finally wakes up
and takes notice.
This assumption
is based on studies like this—where
foreign proteins were injected into
the wart itself, like a measles-mumps-
rubella vaccine straight into the wart—
which compared to placebo, appeared to
accelerate the immune clearance process.
The problem, of course, is that
injections hurt, and 30% of the kids
that got their warts injected with the
vaccine suffered a flu-like syndrome.
Yikes! OK, scratch that.
What else do we got?
Within a few months any placebo treatment
will work in about a quarter of the cases.
So if you put duct tape on 100 warts and
23 go away, that wouldn't mean much.
The traditional medical therapies, acid
treatments and freezing treatments,
bump the cure rate up to about 50%.
So if you were really serious about
testing the efficacy of duct tape,
you would pit it head to head
against one of those,
and that's exactly what happened.
The efficacy of duct tape vs cryotherapy
in the treatment of the common wart.
Cryotherapy is one of the treatments
of choice for many pediatricians.
Objective: To determine if application
of duct tape is as effective
as cryotherapy in the treatment
of common warts.
Patients were randomized to receive
either liquid nitrogen applied
to each wart or
duct tape occlusion.
When I heard about treating
warts with duct tape,
I had this image where they were like
trying to rip them off or something.
No, no, no, no. They're just applying a
little circle of duct tape every week or so.
Although there had been a few
anecdotal reports of using tape,
no prospective, randomized controlled
trial had yet been performed until
this study, which found that the duct
tape was not only equal to but exceeded
the efficacy of cryotherapy, which
worked in 60% of the cases,
but 85% of the duct tape
patients were cured—significantly
more effective than cryotherapy
for treatment of the common wart.
More effective and fewer side effects.
The only adverse effect observed
in the duct tape group during
our study was a small,
minimal amount of local irritation and
redness, whereas cryotherapy hurts.
You want to hear the saddest thing?
One young child actually vomited in fear
of pain before each cryotherapy session.
They were like torturing the poor kid.
Cryotherapy can cause pain and
bloody blisters that can get infected
and mess up your nail bed.
So, duct tape: more effective, fewer
side effects and more convenient.
Compare applying a little duct tape at
home to making multiple clinic visits,
dragging the poor kid
back every two weeks.
I mean it's like a win-win-win.
Duct tape can now be offered
as a nonthreatening, painless,
and inexpensive technique for
the treatment of warts in children.
I mean how much does a
little piece of duct tape cost?
It's like a win-win-win-win.
Ah, but the money you save
is the money the doctor loses.
There's no way the medical profession is
going to just let this go unchallenged.
Further studies were performed
and failed to show an effect,
and so we end up in the medical
literature with conclusions like this:
"Is duct tape effective
for treating warts?"
Bottom line?
No. Huh.
Is duct tape really not
effective after all,
or was there some kind of critical
design flaw in the follow-up studies?
And so even if the effectiveness of duct
tape is shown to be merely equivalent
to that of cryotherapy, it would
be better; and it was shown to be
even more effective,
in fact maybe most effective.
Compared to 10 other wart treatments,
duct tape beat out them all
in terms of effectiveness,
and also in terms of cost—
cheaper than all but the DN option,
which stands for Do Nothing.
Compared to the most cost-effective
prescription treatments available,
OTC duct tape, meaning over-the-counter
duct tape, is 10 times cheaper.
It's an unusual and welcome event in
health care when a common ailment
is proven equally amenable
to an inexpensive, tolerable,
and safe alternative therapy.
Finally today,
I ask and answer if there really is
such a thing as adrenal fatigue.
Many seeking treatment
for common nonspecific symptoms
are led to believe
they are suffering
from some sort
of hormonal deficiency.
"Adrenal fatigue"
is the prototypical example.
Chiropractor-coined in 1998,
the invented diagnosis
has since been embraced
by naturopaths,
functional medicine,
and anti-aging doctors.
But does adrenal fatigue
even exist?
The alleged condition is said
to result from chronic stress
leading to an "overuse"
of the adrenal glands
and their eventual
functional decline.
Symptoms supposedly include
fatigue, body aches,
sleep issues,
and digestive problems,
at least
according to the websites
not so coincidentally selling
a suite of supplements
to remedy it.
It will come as no surprise
that the originator
of the term
sells supplements
on his website
to treat it
for $200 a month.
But it may not be
an actual medical condition.
The symptoms people have
are real,
but they just may be caused
by something else,
for example, sleep apnea,
chronic fatigue syndrome,
or fibromyalgia.
Saliva tests for adrenal
hormone levels are not reliable,
with studies showing so-called
"adrenal fatigue" patients
having higher levels
than controls,
similar levels,
or lower levels,
"an almost systematic finding
of conflicting results."
There is an actual disease
of adrenal insufficiency
known as Addison's disease,
which is diagnosed
with an ACTH stimulation test.
You inject people with
adrenocorticotropic hormone,
the signal your brain uses
to get your adrenal glands
to pump out
the stress hormone cortisol,
and if your adrenals
don't respond,
that shows your adrenal glands
must be in trouble.
But inject those
presumed to be suffering
from chronic stress and fatigue
with ACTH
and sometimes you even get
a greater rise in cortisol,
disproving the notion
that stress causes
the adrenals to "burn out."
But wait,
you were diagnosed with "AF,"
given corticosteroids,
and now you feel great,
so it must have been real.
That's the thing
about corticosteroids, though.
One of the side effects is
a euphoric sense of well-being.
The problem is
that even low doses
can increase the risk
of osteoporosis,
psychiatric and metabolic
disorders, muscle damage,
glaucoma, sleep disturbances,
and cardiovascular diseases.
But wait, you took some
"adrenal support" supplements,
checked the labels,
confirmed they don't have
any hormones,
and still felt better.
They lie.
Researchers checked the 12 most
popular adrenal support supplements,
and every single one
contained hidden hormones,
none of which were declared
on the product labels.
All contained thyroid hormone
and most a steroid hormone
as well,
pregnenolone, budesonide,
androstenedione, progesterone,
cortisone, or cortisol.
Adrenal fatigue reminds me
of what used to be called
"electromagnetic
hypersensitivity,"
now referred to
in the medical literature
as "idiopathic
environmental intolerance
attributed to
electromagnetic fields,"
unspecific symptoms
supposedly triggered
by things like cell phones.
There have been
at least 46 studies
involving more than 1,000 people
that claim to be affected,
yet when put to the test
in blinded trials
the studies
near universally failed
to show that anyone
could even detect the fields.
Why don't journalists covering
these stories mention the data?
Because there are
snake-oil salesmen
profiting off
the perceived condition,
selling all matter of
so-called "protective" gadgets
that viciously attack anyone
even daring to mention
the science,
accusing them
of denying the reality
of people's symptoms.
But it's arguably the opposite.
They are the ones
hindering sufferers
from getting to the bottom
of what is actually causing
their symptoms.
Similarly, hawking
unproven tests and treatments
for adrenal fatigue
could delay the diagnosis
of a real, treatable condition.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My latest book, “How Not to Age”
is out now,
which premiered at #2 on the
New York Times Best Sellers list.
Check it out at your
local public library.
Of course, all the proceeds
I receive of the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is itself a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads,
no corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.